Mary Butler
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Mary Butler papers
1853-1946, bulk 1884-1946
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Butler, Mary
1.6 linear feet
The papers of landscape painter Mary Butler date from 1853-1946, bulk 1884-1946, and measure 1.6 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material, correspondence, and records relating to Butler's long participation in the Fellowship of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. Also found are notes and writings, a scrapbook, printed material, and photographs of Butler, her friends, her studio in Ogunquit, Maine, her landscape paintings, and exhibition installations.
Provenance
The Mary Butler papers were donated in 2005 by Rachel F. Armstrong, the artist's niece.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Mary Butler was born on October 27, 1865 in Uwachlan, Pennsylvania, the daughter of James and Rachel M. (James) Butler.
Butler began her education at the Darlington Seminary. She studied painting at the Philadelphia School of Design for Women (now the Moore College of Art) under William Sartain and Robert Henri, graduating in 1894. Between 1896 and 1902, she studied at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts under William Merritt Chase and Celia Beaux. From 1897 to 1898, she studied at the Académie Colarossi in Paris with Gustave Courtois, René François Xavier Prinet, and Jean-Antoine Injalbert.
She attended a summer school conducted by William Merritt Chase at Shinnacock Hills, and later studied under Robert Henri and Edward W. Redfield. With Redfield, she spent a season at Centre Bridge, Pennsylvania. Butler was primarily a landscape painter and traveled widely in the United States and Europe to find unusual and inspiring views. She also spent summers in Ogunquit and on Monhegan Island, Maine.
In 1909, Butler joined the Fellowship of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts and served as President of that organization from 1921 to 1937. During her tenure, she inaugurated traveling exhibitions, a picture purchasing fund and, in 1915, the Thouron Fund for aid of needy artists.
Throughout her career Butler exhibited extensively and promoted the arts in Philadelphia.
Mary Butler died on March 16, 1946.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of landscape painter Mary Butler date from 1853-1946, bulk 1884-1946, and measure 1.6 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material, correspondence, and records relating to Butler's long participation in the Fellowship of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. Also found are notes and writings, a scrapbook, printed material, and photographs of Butler, her friends, her studio in Ogunquit, Maine, her landscape paintings, and exhibition installations.
Biographical material includes genealogical notes on Butler's early family history, biographical accounts, teaching certificates, and letters of recommendation from Butler's instructors including William Merritt Chase, Robert Henri, and William Sartain.
Found within the papers are correspondence with family members, including letters to her cousin Edgar Butler letters from her friend Mrs. Thomas Eakins; and miscellaneous scattered letters from various colleagues including George Biddle, Dorothy Grafly, Thornton Oakley, and Alice Kent Stoddard concerning various topics. Correspondence regarding exhibitions is with arts organizations and colleagues including Henry Thouron and S. Walter Norris.
There are files documenting Butler's long participation in the Fellowship of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, including a letter from Joseph Pennell, notes, writings, and printed material. Additional printed material includes a scrapbook of clippings, and exhibition announcements and catalogs. Photographs are of Butler, her friends, her studio in Ogunquit, Maine, views of the Maine coast and of Cathedral Crag in Washington State, Butler's landscape paintings, and miscellaneous exhibition installations.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged into seven series. Each series is arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1884-1945 (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1853-1944 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 3: File for the Fellowship of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1917-1946 (Box 1; 14 folders)
Series 4: Notes and Writings, 1905-1938 (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1908-1942 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1894-1944 (Box 2; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1870-1945 (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts
Subjects-Topical:
Women painters -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Landscape painters -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Writings; Scrapbooks
Names:
Biddle, George, 1885-; Chase, William Merritt, 1849-1916; Eakins, Susan Macdowell; Grafly, Dorothy, 1896-; Henri, Robert, 1865-1929; Norris, S. Walter; Oakley, Thornton, 1881-1953; Pennell, Joseph, 1857-1926; Sartain, William, 1843-1924; Stoddard, Alice Kent Pearson, 1885-1976; Thouron, Henry
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1884-1945, Series 1:; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  Biographical material includes genealogical notes, biographical accounts, teaching certificates, letters of recommendation from Butler's instructors including William Merritt Chase, Robert Henri, and William Sartain, membership certificates, hand-drawn menu cards, an award plaque, a medical report concerning her right thumb, and miscellaneous receipts for art supplies, travel expenses, and for donations of artwork.
  - Genealogical Notes, 1894-1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Accounts for Mary Butler, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Teaching Certificates, 1884-1886 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1884-1906, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Membership Certificates, 1897, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hand-Drawn Menu Cards, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Award Plaque; Medical Report, 1914-1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1892-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1853-1944, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
  Family correspondence is between Butler and family members including her cousin, Edgar Butler. There are letters from her friend Mrs. Thomas Eakins, and scattered miscellaneous letters from various colleagues including George Biddle, Dorothy Grafly, Thornton Oakley, and Alice Kent Stoddard. Correspondence concerning exhibitions is with arts organizations and colleagues including Henry Thouron and S. Walter Norris, and includes prospectuses, lists of artwork, and a few price lists.
  - Correspondence with Family Members, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Family Members, 1853-1881 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Family Members, 1882-1884 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Family Members, 1897, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Correspondence with Family Members, 1898, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Correspondence with Family Members, 1899-1903 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence with Family Members, 1912-1915 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence with Family Members, 1923-1929 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with Family Members, 1930-1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters to Edgar Butler, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters from Mrs. Thomas Eakins, 1936-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1907-1910 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1925, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1926, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1935, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1937, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-50)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1938, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 51-52)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1942, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 54-55)
  - Correspondence Concerning Exhibitions, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1896-1909 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1912-1922 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1927-1934 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1935-1942 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Fellowship of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts Files, 1917-1946, Series 3:; (Box 1; 14 folders)
  These files include letters including one from Joseph Pennell, notes and writings, and miscellaneous printed material pertaining to Butler's long participation in the Fellowship of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. Also included is material concerning a Fellowship banquet honoring Butler and a membership purchase of Butler's painting in conjunction with an exhibition at McClees Galleries.
  - Letters, 1919-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Notes and Writings, 1935-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1924-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Clippings, 1917-1926 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1926-1937 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - File Concerning Banquet for Mary Butler, 1936, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 70-72)
  - File Concerning McClees Galleries Exhibition and Purchase of Painting by Mary Butler, 1944, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 73-78)
- Notes and Writings, 1905-1938, Series 4:; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  This series includes address lists, lists of artwork, lists of exhibitions, notes on travel to Ireland, and miscellaneous notes and writings.
  - Address List, undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Address Book, 1908-1925 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Lists of Artwork, 1905-1938, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 81-82)
  - Lists of Exhibitions, 1924-1933 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Notes on Travel to Ireland, 1912, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 84-85)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1919-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Writings by Others, undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 88)
- Scrapbook, 1908-1942, Series 5:; (Box 1; 5 folders)
  One scrapbook contains clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and a list of artwork.
  - Dismantled Scrapbook, 1908-1942, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 89-93)
- Printed Material, 1894-1944, Series 6:; (Box 2; 0.4 linear feet)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and tickets and passes for exhibitions, the Touring-Club de France, and for entrance into public parks. Also found are programs, brochures, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2 (hol), Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1908-1911 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1912-1913 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1914-1924 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1925 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1926-1929 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1930-1932 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1933-1938 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1941-1942 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated (Box 2 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1894-1913 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1914-1915 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1921-1922 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1923-1925 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1926-1928 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1930 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 16)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1931 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1932-1934 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1935-1938 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940-1944 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1918-1936 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Tickets and Passes, 1897-1916, undated (Box 2 (hol), Folder 22)
  - Programs, 1897-1916 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 23)
  - Brochures, 1897-1935 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1896-1935, undated (Box 2 (hol), Folder 25)
- Photographs, circa 1870-1945, Series 7:; (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Mary Butler, her friends, her studio in Ogunquit, Maine, and views of the Maine coast and of Cathedral Crag in Washington State. There is one folder of photographs of Butler's exhibition installations. Most of the photographs are of her landscape paintings of scenes in the United States, Canada, Europe, and Norway.
  - Photographs of Mary Butler, circa 1890-1945, (2 folders) (Box 3 (pam), Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs of Mary Butler in her Ogunquit Studio, circa 1900 (Box 3 (pam), Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Interior of Ogunquit Studio, circa 1900 (Box 3 (pam), Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Friends, circa 1870-1900 (Box 3 (pam), Folder 5)
  - Photographs of the Maine Coast and of Cathedral Crag, 1936, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3 (pam), Folder 6-7)
  - Photographs of Paintings of Cornwall, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Paintings of Scotland, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Paintings of Ireland, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Paintings of the Pyrenees, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Paintings of Norway, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Paintings of the Canadian Rockies, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Paintings of Nova Scotia, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Paintings of Maine, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Paintings of New Hampshire, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Paintings of the Catskills, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Landscape Paintings, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3 (pam), Folder 18-19)
  - Photographs of Exhibition Installations, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 20)